<!--<?xml-model href="sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>-->

<?xml-model href="../project-schema/sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<xml>
      <bibl>
            <author>Jurgen Shperdhea</author>
            <title level="a">Kiev: The Largest Encirclement In The History Of Warfare</title>
            <title>War History Online</title>
            <date when="2019-04-02">April 2 2019</date>
            <ref target="URL"
                  >https://www.warhistoryonline.com/instant-articles/the-largest-encirclement-warfare.html</ref>
      </bibl>
      <desc>
            <p>More than <casualties n="600000">600,000 people</casualties> were lost during this
                  battle, including those who had gone missing or been taken prisoner as well as
                  those who were killed.</p>
      </desc>

      <body>
            <p>The First Battle of <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city> began on <date when="1941-08-07"
                        >August 7, 1941</date>. It was one of the greatest stages of Operation
                  Barbarossa with attacks, resistance, and counterattacks all failing. This was the
                  situation on the Soviet’s Southwestern Front.</p>

            <p>It all happened too fast and escalated even faster. The German Army moved quickly
                  towards <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city> and tried to capture the city. It would be
                  remembered as the greatest encirclement in the history of warfare.</p>

            <p>German armored tank divisions could move with speed. The troops were well-trained and
                  had the necessary equipment. They advanced hundreds of miles into Soviet territory
                  to further the ambitions of their leader.</p>

            <p><leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> wanted to deprive the Soviets of their
                  resources and factories, so he put in place Directive 33 on <date
                        when="1941-07-19">July 19, 1941</date>. The world was holding its breath to
                  see who would be the victor in this vicious battle between two superpowers.</p>

            <p>The German generals were against <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler's</leader>
                  directives. They were of the opinion that <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> had to
                  be captured first. But <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> had other ideas
                  in mind.</p>

            <p>After the order had been given, two smaller groups were detached from <army
                        group="center">Army Group Center</army> — the <army group="Panzer" n="2">2nd
                        Panzer Group</army> and the <army group="infantry" n="2">2nd Army</army>.
                  They were sent south, on a mission to start the encirclement of The Southwestern
                  Front. They would meet with the <army group="Panzer" n="1">1st Panzer</army> of
                        <army group="south">Army South Group</army> which was headed towards the
                  southwestern side.</p>

            <p>The Southwestern Front, which was held by the Red Army, was trying to counterattack
                  and break through the circle, but the Germans were everywhere.</p>

            <p>By <date when="1941-09-12">September 12, 1941</date>, the <army group="Panzer" n="1"
                        >1st Panzer Group</army> had progressed far enough north that they were
                  crossing the Dnieper river. On <date when="1941-09-16">September 16</date>, they
                  made contact with the <army group="Panzer" n="2">2nd Panzer Group</army> and
                  continued south, arriving at the town of <city name="Lokhvista">Lokhvista</city>,
                  120 miles east of <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city>.</p>

            <p>The Soviet <leader name="Semyon Budyonny">General Budyonny</leader>, who was in
                  charge of The Southwestern Front, started to realize that they would soon be stuck
                  and surrounded.</p>

            <p>The Red Army was at the mercy of the Germans. <leader name="Semyon Budyonny"
                        >Budyonny</leader> and his men were left with no options. The Germans had
                  managed to capture them successfully through a massive encirclement movement. With
                  the German Army’s infantry joining together in this way, the fate of the Soviets
                  was sealed at <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city>, even though they fought hard.</p>

            <p>Kiev had effectively fallen by <date when="1941-09-19">September 19</date>, but the
                  encircled troops continued to put up a fight. The Red Army’s <army n="5"
                        >5th</army>, <army n="26">26th</army>, <army n="21">21st</army>, <army
                        n="38">38th</army>, and <army n="37">37th</army> Army were captured inside
                  the circle. They fought for about ten more days, but everything was falling
                  apart.</p>

            <p>The Southwestern Front was about to disintegrate, and a lot of lives would be lost
                  among the civilians too. More than <casualties n="600000">600,000
                        people</casualties> were lost during this battle, including those who had
                  gone missing or been taken prisoner as well as those who were killed.</p>

            <p>Some troops tried to withdraw. Soviet Generals like <leader name="Mikhail Kirponos"
                        >Mikhail Kirponos</leader> and others were murdered. Only a fraction of
                        <survivors n="15000">15,000 troop</survivors>s managed to escape the
                  encirclement.</p>

            <p>
                  <leader name="Heinz Guderian">General Guderian’s</leader> decision to turn south
                  was one of the moves that enabled the encirclement to succeed. The Soviets, on the
                  other hand, had been scattered and that weakened them. Their defensive and
                  counter-offensive tactics resulted in a terrible defeat.</p>

            <p> Germany’s initial invasion started out with more than <manpower who="Germany"
                        n="500000">500,000 men</manpower> while the Soviets had more than <manpower
                        who="Soviet Union" n="700000">700,000</manpower>. During the battle, the
                  Germans lost only <casualties n="45000">45,000 men</casualties> while the number
                  of Soviet causalities was staggering. More than <casualties n="600000">600,000 men
                        were either killed, captured or missing</casualties>. In addition, more than
                        <casualties n="84000">84,000 were sick or wounded.</casualties></p>

            <p> The Red Army’s loss of resources after this battle made it hard for them to recover.
                  More than <casualties n="400">400 tanks had been destroyed</casualties> as well as
                        <casualties n="343">343 aircraft</casualties> and nearly <casualties
                        n="30000">30,000 guns and mortars.</casualties></p>

            <p>It’s possible that this battle subtly impacted on the course of the war. If <leader
                        name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> had not rejected the advice of all his
                  generals and had proceeded to take <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> instead,
                  maybe history would have been different. The Germans might have won this battle,
                  but their delay in taking <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> was fatal.</p>

            <p>This opinion is borne out by one of the German commanders who commented after World
                  War 2 was over that going for <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city> first was a huge
                  mistake. Choosing <city name="Kiev">Kiev</city> meant that <operation name="Typhoon">Operation Typhoon</operation> was delayed until <date
                        when="1941-10-01">October</date>. He said that if they had gone for <city
                        name="Moscow">Moscow</city> first, they would have been able to capture the
                  city before the cold Russian winter set in.</p>
      </body>
</xml>
