<?xml-model href="../../../sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <bibl>
        <author>History.com Editors</author>
        <title level="a">Siege of Leningrad begins</title>
        <title>History Channel</title>
        <date when="2019-07-28">July 28 2019</date>
        <ref target="URL"
            >https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/siege-of-leningrad-begins</ref>
    </bibl>

    <desc>
        <p>During World War II, German forces begin their siege of <city name="Leningrad"
                >Leningrad</city>, a major industrial center and the USSR’s second-largest city. The
            German armies were later joined by Finnish forces that advanced against <city
                name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> down the Karelian Isthmus. The siege of <city
                name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>, also known as the 900-Day Siege though it lasted
            a grueling 872 days, resulted in the <casualties n="1000000">deaths of some one million
                of the city’s civilians and Red Army defenders</casualties>.</p>
    </desc>

    <body>
        <p><city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>, formerly St. Petersburg, capital of the Russian
            Empire, was one of the initial targets of the German invasion of <date when="1941-06-22"
                >June 1941</date>. As German armies raced across the western Soviet Union,
            three-quarters of <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad’s</city> industrial plants and
            hundreds of thousands of its inhabitants were evacuated to the east. More than two
            million residents remained, however, and the evacuated were replaced by refugees who
            fled to <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> ahead of the German advance. All
            able-bodied persons in the city–men, women, and children–were enlisted to build antitank
            fortifications along <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad’s</city> edge. By the <date
                when="1941-07-31">end of July</date>, German forces had cut the <city name="Moscow"
                >Moscow</city>-<city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> railway and were penetrating
            the outer belt of the fortifications around <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>. On
                <date when="1941-09-08">September 8</date>, German forces besieged the city, but
            they were held at bay by <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad’s</city> fortifications and
            its <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="200000">200,000 Red Army defenders</manpower>. That
            day, a German air bombardment set fire to warehouses containing a large part of <city
                name="Leningrad">Leningrad’s</city> scant food supply.</p>

        <p>Aiming to tighten the noose around <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>, the Germans
            launched an offensive to the east in <date when="1941-10-01">October</date> and cut off
            the last highways and rail lines south of the city. Meanwhile, Finnish forces advanced
            down the Karelian Isthmus (which had been seized from Finland by the Soviets during the
            Russo-Finnish War of 1939 to 1940) and besieged <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>
            from the north. By <date when="1941-11-01">early November</date>, the city was almost
            completely encircled, and only across Lake Ladoga was a supply lifeline possible.</p>

        <p>German artillery and air bombardments came several times a day during the first months of
            the siege. The daily ration for civilians was reduced to 125 grams of bread, no more
            than a thick slice. Starvation set in by <date when="1941-12-01">December</date>,
            followed by the coldest winter in decades, with temperatures falling to -40 degrees
            Fahrenheit. People worked through the winter in makeshift armament factories without
            roofs, building the weapons that kept the Germans just short of victory.</p>

        <p>Residents burned books and furniture to stay warm and searched for food to supplement
            their scarce rations. Animals from the city zoo were consumed early in the siege,
            followed before long by household pets. Wallpaper paste made from potatoes was scraped
            off the wall, and leather was boiled to produce an edible jelly. Grass and weeds were
            cooked, and scientists worked to extract vitamins from pine needles and tobacco dust.
            Hundreds, perhaps thousands, resorted to cannibalizing the dead, and in a few cases
            people were murdered for their flesh. The Leningrad police struggled to keep order and
            formed a special division to combat cannibalism.</p>

        <p>Across frozen Lake Ladoga, trucks made it to Leningrad with supplies, but not enough.
            Thousands of residents, mostly children and the elderly, were evacuated across the lake,
            but many more remained in the city and succumbed to starvation, the bitter cold, and the
            relentless German air attacks. In 1942 alone, <casualties n="600000">the siege claimed
                some 600,000 lives</casualties>. In the summer, barges and other ships braved German
            air attack to cross Lake Ladoga to <city name="Stalingrad">Leningrad</city> with
            supplies.</p>

        <p>In <date when="1943-01-01">January 1943</date>, Red Army soldiers broke through the
            German line, rupturing the blockade and creating a more efficient supply route along the
            shores of Lake Ladoga. For the rest of the winter and then during the next, the “road of
            life” across the frozen Lake Ladoga kept Leningrad alive. Eventually, an oil pipeline
            and electric cables were laid on the lake bed. In the <date when="1943-06-01">summer of
                1943</date>, vegetables planted on any open ground in the city supplemented
            rations.</p>

        <p>In <date when="1944-01-01">early 1944</date>, Soviet forces approached <city
                name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city>, forcing German forces to retreat southward from
            the city on <date when="1944-01-27">January 27</date>. The siege was over. A giant
            Soviet offensive to sweep the USSR clean of its invaders began in May. <casualties
                n="1000000">The 872-day siege of Leningrad cost an estimated one million Soviet
                lives, perhaps hundreds of thousands more</casualties>. The Soviet government
            awarded the Order of Lenin to the people of <city name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> in
                <date when="1945-01-01">1945</date>, paying tribute to their endurance during the
            grueling siege. The city did not regain its prewar population of three million until the
            1960s.</p>
    </body>
</xml>
