
<?xml-model href="GitHub/operation-barbarossa/project-schema/sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <bibl>
        <author>C N Truema</author>
        <title level="a">The Battle for Moscow</title>
        <title>History Learning Site</title>
        <date when="2019-04-02">September 21 2019</date>
        <ref target="URL"
            >https://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/world-war-two/world-war-two-and-eastern-europe/the-battle-for-moscow/</ref>
    </bibl>
    <desc>
        <p>The Battle for <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> – the Germans code-named it <operation
                name="Typhoon">‘Operation Typhoon</operation>’ – started on <date when="1941-10-02"
                >October 2nd 1941</date>. The capture of <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>, Russia’s
            capital, was seen as vital to the success of <operation name="Barbarossa">‘Operation
                Barbarossa‘</operation>. Hitlerbelieved that once the heart – <city name="Moscow"
                >Moscow</city> – had been cut out of Russia, the whole nation would collapse.</p>
    </desc>

    <body>
        <p>The initial stages of <operation name="Barbarossa">Barbarossa</operation> have been seen
            as massively successful for the Germans and catastrophic for the Russians. Few would
            deny the success of the German attack – <casualties n="28" unit="divisions">28 Russian
                divisions</casualties> were put out of action in just three weeks and more than 70
            divisions lost <casualties n="50" unit="percent">50% or more of their men and
                equipment</casualties>.Blitzkrieg had ploughed through the Red Army. <leader
                name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler’s</leader> belief that the Red Army would crumble seemed
            to be coming true. However, the Germans had also suffered in their attacks on Russia. By
            one month into <operation name="Barbarossa">Barbarossa</operation>, the Germans had lost
            over <casualties n="100000">100,000 men</casualties>, <casualties n="50" unit="percent"
                >50% of their tanks</casualties> and over <casualties n="1200">1,200
                planes</casualties>. With its army split between east and west Europe, these were
            heavy casualty figures. <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler’s</leader> belief that the
            Red Army would be crushed also meant that there had been little consideration of the
            Russian winter and very many of the Wehrmacht in Russia had not been equipped with
            proper winter clothing. The battle that raged around <city name="Smolensk"
                >Smolensk</city> had critically held up the advance of the Germans.</p>

        <p>Ironically for an army that was to suffer from the Russian winter, <operation
                name="Typhoon">‘Operation Typhoon’</operation> started off in ideal weather
            conditions on <date when="1941-10-02">October 2nd, 1941</date>. <leader
                name="Fedor von Bock">Field Marshall von Bock</leader> had been given overall
            command of the attack on <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>. <leader name="Adolf Hitler"
                >Hitler</leader> had ordered that units in other parts of the Russian campaign be
            moved to <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> – <leader name="Erich Hoepner">General
                Hoepner’s</leader>
            <army group="Panzer" n="4">IV Panzer group</army> had been moved from <city
                name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> – hence why the Germans did not have sufficient
            men to launch an attack on the city and why it had to be besieged. For the attack,
                <leader name="Fedor von Bock">Bock</leader> had at his disposal <manpower
                who="Germany" n="1000000">1 million men</manpower>, <manpower who="Germany" n="1700"
                >1,700 tanks</manpower>, <manpower who="Germany" n="19500">19,500 artillery
                guns</manpower> and <manpower who="Germany" n="950">950 combat aircraft</manpower> –
                <manpower who="Germany" n="50" unit="percent">50% of all the German men in
                Russia</manpower>, <manpower who="Germany" n="75" unit="percent">75% of all the
                tanks</manpower> and <manpower who="Germany" n="33" unit="percent">33% of all the
                planes</manpower>. To defend <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>, the Russians had
                <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="500000">under 500,000 men</manpower>, <manpower
                who="Soviet Union" n="900">less than 900 tanks</manpower> and <manpower
                who="Soviet Union" n="300">just over 300 combat planes</manpower>.</p>

        <p><leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> had made it clear to his generals what he
            wanted from them. <leader name="Franz Halder">Chief-of-Staff Halder</leader> wrote in
            his diary:</p>

        <p><quote from="Franz Halder">“It is the <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Führer’s</leader>
                unshakable decision to raze <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> and <city
                    name="Leningrad">Leningrad</city> to the ground, so as to be completely relieved
                of the population of these cities, which we would otherwise have to feed through the
                winter. The task of destroying the cities is to be carried out by aircraft.”</quote>
            On <date when="1941-10-12">October 12th</date>, ten days into the attack by <leader
                name="Fedor von Bock">Bock’s</leader>
            <army group="center">Army Group Centre</army>, he received a further order from German
            Supreme Command:</p>

        <p><quote from="German Supreme Command">“The <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Führer</leader> has
                reaffirmed his decision that the surrender of <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> will
                not be accepted, even if it is offered by the enemy.”</quote> The order went on to
            instruct Bock that gaps could be left open for people in <city name="Moscow"
                >Moscow</city> to escape into the interior of Russia where administrating them would
            cause chaos.</p>

        <p>The attack started well for the Germans. The Russians found it difficult to communicate
            with all parts of their defences and infantry divisions frequently had to face tanks
            without air or artillery support. By <date when="1941-10-07">October 7th</date>, even
                <leader name="Georgy Zhukov">Marshall Zhukov</leader> was forced to admit that all
            the major roads to <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> were open to the Germans. Large
            parts of the Red Army had been encircled at <city name="Vyazma">Vyazma</city> (the <army
                n="19">19th</army>, <army n="24">24th</army>, <army n="29">29th</army>, <army n="30"
                >30th</army>, <army n="32">32nd</army> and <army n="43">43rd armies</army>) and at
            two places near <city name="Bryansk">Bryansk</city> (the <army n="3">3rd</army>, <army
                n="13">13th</army> and <army n="50">50th armies</army>) such was the ferocity of the
            German attack and the state of the Russian army then.</p>

        <p>Ironically, it was these armies that had been trapped near <city name="Vyazma"
                >Vyazma</city> and <city name="Bryansk">Bryansk</city> that caused the Germans their
            first major problem in the attack on <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>. The Germans
            could not simply leave nine Russian armies in their rear as they advanced east. They had
            to take on these trapped armies. By doing so, they slowed down their advance to <city
                name="Moscow">Moscow</city> to such an extent that the Red Army was given sufficient
            breathing space to reorganise itself and its defences under the command of <leader
                name="Georgy Zhukov">Marshall Georgy Zhukov</leader> – the man who ‘never lost a
            battle’. The choice of <leader name="Georgy Zhukov">Zhukov</leader> was an enlightened
            one:</p>

        <p><quote from="Konstantin Rokossovsky">“In my view, <leader name="Georgy Zhukov"
                    >Zhukov</leader> remains always a man of strong will and decisiveness, clear and
                gifted, exacting, persistent and purposeful. These qualities are all, undoubtedly,
                indispensable to a great military leader, and <leader name="Georgy Zhukov"
                    >Zhukov</leader> has them.”</quote>Marshall of the Soviet Union <leader
                name="Konstantin Rokossovsky">Rokossovsky</leader>
            <leader name="Georgy Zhukov">Zhukov</leader> organised his defence along the so-called
            ‘Mozhaysk Line’. The Germans attacked this line on <date when="1941-10-10">October
                10th</date> – by which time they had dealt with the Russians at <city name="Vyazma"
                >Vyazma</city>. Though on paper the delay to the Germans had been mere days, to the
            Russians it allowed them time to move their forces to where <leader name="Georgy Zhukov"
                >Zhukov</leader> believed they would be needed. Even so, the Germans broke through
            the Mozhaysk Line at a number of places and for all of <leader name="Georgy Zhukov"
                >Zhukov's</leader> work, <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> was still very much
            threatened. Parts of the German army got to 45 miles of <city name="Moscow"
                >Moscow’s</city> centre before the tide was turned and a stalemate developed with
            little movement on either side.</p>

        <p>On <date when="1941-11-13">November 13th</date>, senior German commanders met at <city
                name="Orsha">Orsha</city>. It was at this meeting that the decision was taken to
            start a second assault on <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>. During the stalemate, the
            Russians had sent <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="100000">100,000 more men</manpower> to
            defend <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> with an <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="300"
                >extra 300 tanks</manpower> and <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="2000">2,000
                artillery guns</manpower>.</p>

        <p><city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> itself had been turned into a fortress with 422 miles
            of anti-tank ditches being dug, 812 miles of barbed wire entanglements and some 30,000
            firing points. Resistance groups had also been organised to fight both in the city,
            should the Germans enter <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> and in the area around the
            city. In all, about 10,000 people from <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city> were involved
            in planned resistance activities. <leader name="P A Artemyev">Lieutenant-General P A
                Artemyev</leader> was given the task of defending the city. Between 100 and 120
            trains provided the city with what was required on a daily basis at a time when the
            Germans could only average 23 trains a day when they required 70 – such was the
            effectiveness of partisan activity.</p>

        <p>The second assault narrowed its target area so that as much fire power could be
            concentrated in one area as possible. The belief that was held was that if one small
            part of the city was entered, all the defences surrounding it would fall once the might
            of the Panzer units fanned out. However, the attack met with fierce Russian resistance.
            The Germans got as far forward as 18 miles from <city name="Moscow">Moscow's</city>
            centre (the village of Krasnaya Polyana) but the Russian defence line held out. It is
            said that German reconnaissance units actually got into the outskirts of the city but by
                <date when="1941-11-30">the end of November</date> the whole forward momentum of the
            Germans had stalled. <date when="1941-12-01">By December</date>, the Russians had
            started to counter-attack the Germans. In just 20 days of the second offensive, the
            Germans lost <casualties n="155000">155,000 men (killed, wounded or a victim of
                frostbite)</casualties>, about <casualties n="800">800 tanks</casualties> and
                <casualties n="300">300 artillery guns</casualties>. Whereas the Germans had few men
            in reserve, the Russians had 58 infantry and cavalry divisions in reserve. STAVKA
            proposed to use a number of these divivions to start a counter-offensive against the
            Germans – <leader name="Josef Stalin">Stalin</leader> himself made it clear to <leader
                name="Georgy Zhukov">Zhukov</leader> that he expected a counter-attack to start on
                <date when="1941-12-05">December 5th</date> in the battle zone to the north of <city
                name="Moscow">Moscow</city> and on <date when="1941-12-06">December 6th</date> in
            the battle zone to the south of the city. The attacks took place at the times decreed by
                <leader name="Josef Stalin">Stalin</leader> and they proved highly effective against
            an enemy that was being hit hard by sub-zero winter temperatures – night temperatures of
            -20F were not uncommon.</p>

        <p>The impact of these attacks so unnerved <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> that
            he issued the following order:</p>

        <p>
            <quote from="Adolf Hitler">“The troops must be compelled by the personal influences of
                their commanders, commanding officers, and officers, to resist fanatically on their
                present positions, without regard to enemy breakthroughs on the flanks and in the
                rear. Only by leading their troops in this way can the necessary time be gained for
                movement of reinforcements from the homeland and the West which I have ordered to be
                carried out.”</quote>
            <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> However, his call was in vain. The Wehrmacht
            was pushed back between 60 and 155 miles in places and by <date when="1942-01-01"
                >January 1942</date>, the threat to Moscow had passed. <leader name="Adolf Hitler"
                >Hitler's</leader> response to this was to move <manpower who="Germany" n="800000"
                >800,000 men from the west of Europe to the Eastern Front</manpower> – thus ending
            forever any chance, however very small it may have been, of <operation name="Sealion"
                >‘Operation Sealion‘</operation> being carried out. He also dismissed 35 senior
            officers as well – including the <leader name="Walther von Brauchitsch"
                >Commander-in-Chief of the Army, Brauchitsch</leader>, and the three army commanders
            in the field – <leader name="Fedor von Bock">Bock</leader>, <leader
                name="Wilhelm Ritter von Leeb">Leeb</leader> and <leader name="Gerd von Rundstedt"
                >Rundstedt</leader>.</p>
    </body>
</xml>
