<?xml-model href="sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <bibl>
        <author>History.com Editors</author>
        <title level="a">Battle of Stalingrad</title>
        <title>History Channel</title>
        <date when="2019-06-06">June 6 2019</date>
        <ref target="URL"
            >https://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/siege-of-leningrad-begins</ref>
    </bibl>
    <desc><p>The Battle of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> was a brutal military campaign
        between Russian forces and those of Nazi Germany and the Axis powers during World War II.
        The battle is infamous as one of the largest, longest and bloodiest engagements in modern
        warfare: From <date when="1942-08-01" to="1943-02-01">August 1942 through February
            1943</date>, <manpower who="Both" n="2000000">more than two million troops fought in
            close quarters</manpower> – and <casualties n="2000000">nearly two million people were
            killed or injured in the fighting, including tens of thousands of Russian
            civilians</casualties>. But the Battle of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> (one
        of Russia’s important industrial cities) ultimately turned the tide of World War II in favor
        of the Allied forces.</p></desc>

    <body><p>Prelude to the Battle of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city></p>
    <p>In the middle of World War II – having captured territory in much of present-day Ukraine and
        Belarus in the spring of 1942 – Germany’s Wehrmacht forces decided to mount an offensive on
        southern Russia in the summer of that year.</p>

    <p>Under the leadership of ruthless head of state <leader name="Joseph Stalin">Joseph
            Stalin</leader>, Russian forces had already successfully rebuffed a German attack on the
        western part of the country – one that had the ultimate goal of taking <city name="Moscow"
            >Moscow</city> – <date when="1941-11-01" to="1942-03-01">during the winter of
            1941-42</date>. However, <leader name="Joseph Stalin">Stalin’s</leader> Red Army had
        suffered significant losses in the fighting, both in terms of manpower and weaponry.</p>

    <p><leader name="Joseph Stalin">Stalin</leader> and his generals, including future Soviet Union
        leader <leader name="Nikita Khrushchev">Nikita Khrushchev</leader>, fully expected another
        Nazi attack to be aimed at <city name="Moscow">Moscow</city>. However, <leader
            name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> and the Wehrmacht had other ideas.</p>

    <p>They set their sights on <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>, because the city served
        as an industrial center in Russia, producing, among other important goods, artillery for the
        country’s troops. The Volga River, which runs through the city, was also an important
        shipping route connecting the western part of the country with its distant eastern
        regions.</p>

    <p>Ultimately, <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Adolf Hitler</leader> wanted the Wehrmacht to occupy
            <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>, seeing its value for propaganda purposes,
        given that it bore Stalin’s name. For similar reasons, the Russians felt a special need to
        protect it.</p>

    <p>When <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> proclaimed that upon taking <city
            name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> all of the city’s male residents would be killed and
        its women deported, the stage was set for a bloody, hard-fought battle. <leader
            name="Joseph Stalin">Stalin</leader> ordered all Russians strong enough to hold a rifle
        to take up arms in defense of the city.</p>

    <p>The <army group="infantry" n="6">6th Army</army> of the Wehrmacht began their assault on
            <date when="1942-08-23">August 23, 1942</date>.</p>

    <p>Battle of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> Begins Russian forces were initially able
        to slow the German Wehrmacht’s advances during a series of brutal skirmishes just north of
            <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>. <leader name="Joseph Stalin"
            >Stalin’s</leader> forces <casualties n="200000">lost more than 200,000
        men</casualties>, but they successfully held off German soldiers.</p>

    <p>With a firm understanding of <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler’s</leader> plans, the
        Russians had already shipped much of the stores of grain and cattle out of <city
            name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>. However, the city’s 400,000-plus residents were not
        evacuated, as the Russian leadership believed their presence would inspire troops.</p>

    <p>Within a few days of launching its attack, Germany’s Luftwaffe air force had rendered the
        Volga River impassable to shipping and had sunk several Russian commercial vessels in the
        process. <date when="1942-08-23" to="1943-02-02">From late August through the end of the
            assault</date>, the Luftwaffe conducted dozens of air strikes on the city.</p>

    <p>The number of civilian casualties is unknown. However, it’s believed that <casualties>tens of
            thousands were killed, and that tens of thousands more were captured and forced into
            slave labor in camps in Germany</casualties>.</p>

    <p>By <date when="1942-09-01">September</date>, the Luftwaffe essentially had control of the
        skies over <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>, and the Russians were getting
        desperate. Workers in the city not involved in war-related weapons production were soon
        asked to take up fighting, often without firearms of their own. Women were enlisted to dig
        trenches at the front lines.</p>

    <p>And yet, the Russians continued to suffer heavy losses. By the <date when="1942-10-01">fall
            of 1942</date>, <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> was in ruins.</p>

    <p><quote from="Joseph Stalin">‘Not a Step Back!’</quote> Despite heavy casualties and the
        pounding delivered by the Luftwaffe, Stalin instructed his forces in the city to not
        retreat, famously decreeing in Order No. 227: <quote from="Joseph Stalin">“Not a step
            back!”</quote> Those who surrendered would be subject to a trial by military tribunal
        and face possible execution.</p>

    <p>With <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="20000">fewer than 20,000 troops</manpower> in the city
        and <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="100">less than 100 tanks</manpower>, Stalin’s generals
        finally began sending reinforcements into the city and surrounding areas. Fighting raged in
        the streets of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>, with both sides using snipers
        poised on the roofs of the city’s buildings.</p>

    <p>Russian generals <leader name="Georgy Zhukov">Georgy Zhukov</leader> and <leader
            name="Aleksandr Vasilevsky">Aleksandr Vasilevsky</leader> organized Russian troops in
        the mountains to the north and west of the city. From there, they launched a counterattack,
        famously known as <operation name="Uranus">Operation Uranus</operation>.</p>

    <p>Although they again sustained significant losses, Russian forces were able to form what in
        essence was a defensive ring around the city by <date when="1942-11-30">late November
            1942</date>, trapping the nearly <manpower who="Germany" n="300000">300,000 German and
            Axis troops</manpower> in the <army group="infantry" n="6">6th Army</army>. This effort
        became the subject of a propaganda film produced after the war, The Battle of <city
            name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>.</p>

    <p>With the Russian blockade limiting access to supplies, German forces trapped in <city
            name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> slowly starved. The Russians would seize upon the
        resulting weakness during the cold, harsh winter months that followed.</p>

    <p>Russian Winter Sets In As Russia’s brutal winter began, Soviet generals knew the Germans
        would be at a disadvantage, fighting in conditions to which they weren’t accustomed. They
        began consolidating their positions around <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>,
        choking off the German forces from vital supplies and essentially surrounding them in an
        ever-tightening noose.</p>

    <p>Thanks to Russian gains in nearby fighting, including in <city name="Rostov"
            >Rostov-on-Don</city>, 250 miles from <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>, the
        Axis forces – mostly Germans and Italians – were stretched thin. Through <operation
            name="Little Saturn">Operation Little Saturn</operation>, the Russians began to break
        the lines of mostly Italian forces to the west of the city.</p>

    <p>At this point, German generals abandoned all efforts to relieve their beleaguered forces
        trapped in <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>. Still, <leader name="Adolf Hitler"
            >Hitler</leader> refused to surrender even as his men slowly starved and ran out of
        ammunition.</p>

    <p>Battle of <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> Ends By <date when="1943-02-02">February
            1943</date>, Russian troops had retaken <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> and
        captured nearly <casualties n="100000">100,000 German soldiers</casualties>, though pockets
        of resistance continued to fight in the city until <date when="1943-03-01">early
            March</date>. Most of the captured soldiers died in Russian prison camps, either as a
        result of disease or starvation.</p>

    <p>The loss at <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city> was the first failure of the war to be
        publicly acknowledged by <leader name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader>. It put <leader
            name="Adolf Hitler">Hitler</leader> and the Axis powers on the defensive, and boosted
        Russian confidence as it continued to do battle on the Eastern Front in World War II.</p>

    <p>In the end, many historians believe the Battle at <city name="Stalingrad">Stalingrad</city>
        marked a major turning point in the conflict. It was the beginning of the march toward
        victory for the Allied forces of Russia, Britain, France and the United States.</p>

    <p>In <date when="2018-02-01">February 2018</date>, Russians gathered in what is now known as Volgograd to celebrate the 75th
        anniversary of the conclusion of the battle that had ravaged their city.</p></body>
</xml>
