<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<timeline>
    <bibl>
        <title level="a">Operation Barbarossa Timeline</title>
        <title>Holocaust Research Project</title>
        <date>2008</date>
        <ref target="URL">http://www.holocaustresearchproject.org/nazioccupation/opbarb.html</ref>
    </bibl>
    <desc>
        <p>Timeline of the German Invasion of the Soviet Union - Up to the Defeat at Stalingrad</p>

        <p>Operation Barbarossa: Was the German codename for the invasion of the USSR which took
            place on 22 June 1941. Launched by Hitler in violation of the existing non-aggression
            treaty with Stalin, it was designed to provide the Reich with 'living space in the
            East'.</p>

        <p>The German dictator had advocated the conquest of the USSR as early as 1924 in his book,
            Mein Kampf. At the same time, the campaign was to lay the foundations for the expected
            conflict with the two Anglo-Saxon powers for primacy as a world power and to free
            Germany of the economic warfare the Allies were waging against it.</p>

        <p>The German invasion marked the beginning of a rapacious war of annihilation and conquest
            in which a scorched earth policy was employed by both sides. Hitler intended a 'ruthless
            Germanization' of the occupied eastern territories, conducted with great severity.</p>

        <p>Orders violating international law, such as the Kommissarbefehl, the order to execute all
            Red Army political commissars, and the 'Barbarossa jurisdiction Decree', which exempted
            German soldiers from prosecution if they committed a crime against any Soviet civilian,
            meant a departure from traditional military conduct for the Wehrmacht. At the same time,
            Einsatzgruppen were to carry out the murder of Jewish and Slav elements of the
            population.</p>
    </desc>
    <body>
        <date>June 22 1941</date> Operation Barbarossa begins: <army group="north"
            leader="Wilhem Ritter von Leeb">Army Group North – Wilhem Ritter von Leeb</army>
        <army group="centre" leader="Feodor Von Bock">Army Group Centre – Feodor Von Bock</army>
        <army group="south" leader="Gerd von Runstedt">Army Group South – Gerd von Runstedt</army>
        Invade Soviet Territory and head for Leningrad, Moscow and Kiev respectively. Easy progress
        is made in the North and Centre but Runstedt meets desperate Soviet resistance in the South.
            <date>June 24 – 30 1941</date> Army Group Centre seals off Soviet resistance into
        pockets at Bialystok, Novogrudok and Volkovysk <date>June 26 1941</date> In the centre,
        Brest Litovsk falls after a four day siege. Manstein’s panzers of Army Group North enter
        Daugavpils <date>July 1 1941</date> In the centre, Heinz Guderian’s panzers cross the
        Berezina. Panzer spearheads of Army Group North cross the Dvina and advance on Pskov.
            <date>July 4 1941</date> Army Group North captures Ostrov and reaches the pre-1939
        Russian frontier. <date>July 9 1941</date> Army Group Centre ends Soviet resistance in the
        Minsk pocket and captures Vitebsk <date>July 10 -11</date> Panzers of Army Group Centre
        cross the Dniepr. In the South, a Soviet counter-offensive by 5th and 6th Armies fails.
        Kleist’s Panzers approach to within ten miles of Kiev. <date>July 15 1941</date> A
        breakthrough in the Centre leads to the encirclement and fall of Smolensk, cutting off a
        Soviet concentration of 300,000 men between Orsha and Smolensk. <date>July 20 1941</date> In
        the Centre, Bock orders Guderian to close the ring at Smolensk before any further advance to
        the East. <date>July 22 1941</date> After a month’s scorching advance Army Group North is
        checked West of Lake Ilmen by the exhaustion of the troops. <date>July 30 194</date>1 In the
        South Kleist begins to seal off the Soviet concentration at Uman <date>August 3 1941</date>
        In the South, Kleist and Stulpnagel seal off the Uman pocket: the inner pincers close.
            <date>August 5 194</date>1 End of Soviet resistance in the Smolensk pocket: Army Group
        Centre has succeeded in breaking out of the Smolensk land-bridge but is still faced with
        determined Soviet counterattacks in the South. Rumanian troops begin the 73 day siege of
        Odessa. <date>August 12 1941</date> Hitler insists on the destruction of the Soviet
        South-West Front before resuming the advance in the Centre, as Guderian heads South towards
        Gomel and Starodub. Army Group North advances on Leningrad from the Luga bridgehead.
            <date>August 23 – 30 1941</date> Guderian heads South belatedly, the Soviet front
        commander Yeremenko prepares to forestall the threat to Kiev from the rear. <date>August 25
            1941</date> Panzers of Army Group South consolidates the Dniepr crossing at
        Dnepropetrovsk: path cleared for the Southern arm of the German pincer movement to engulf
        the Uman/ Kiev concentration. <date>August 30 - September 2 1941</date> Failure of
        Yeremenko’s counter-offensive against Guderian’s flank. <date>September 12 1941</date>
        Kleist heads North from the Cherkassy/ Kremenchug beach-heads. <date>September 15
            1941</date> The outer pincers close: Panzer spearheads of Kleist and Guderian meet at
        Lokhvitsa, trapping four Soviet armies in the Kiev area. <date>September 17 1941</date>
        STAVKA belatedly orders a Soviet withdrawal from Kiev <date>September 18 – 27 1941</date> In
        the South, slaughter and surrenders inside the Kiev pocket. Nearly two thirds of the Red
        Army’s strength on the outbreak of war has already been eliminated. <date>October 23 -24
            1941</date> Army Group South enters Kharkov <date>November 28 1941</date> Army Group
        South is forced to retire from Rostov by heavy Soviet counter-attacks, after an occupation
        of eight days. <date>June 22 1941</date> Drive in the North, Army Group North invades the
        USSR heading for Leningrad <date>June 26 1941</date> Army Group North captures Dugavpils and
        the Dvina river-crossings. <date>June 29 1941</date> Dietl’s force advances on Murmansk from
        Finland, but it is finally halted on the Litsa River. <date>July 10 1941</date> Mannerheim’s
        Karelian Army invades the USSR from Finland heading South-East to clear the Karelian
        Isthmus. <date>July 13 - 16 1941</date> Army Group North spearheads reach the Luga River, 60
        miles short of Leningrad. Mannerheim’s army reaches the Northern shore of Lake Ladoga.
            <date>August 3 - 4 1941</date> Mannerheim begins his drive to recover the Karelian
        Isthmus for Finland. <date>August 8 1941</date> Army Group North advances from the Luga
        bridgeheads. <date>August 16 1941</date> Army Group North reaches Novgorod and crosses the
        Volkhov River. <date>August 27 1941</date> Despite successes Mannerheim refuses to act in
        direct co-operation with Army Group North <date>September 1 194</date>1 German long-range
        artillery begins to bombard Leningrad <date>September 15 1941</date> Army Group North
        completes the encirclement of Leningrad – the siege begins <date>October 23 – 24 1941</date>
        Finnish Southern front stabilised <date>November 7 1941</date> Finnish advance halted on all
        fronts. <date>November 9 1941</date> The vital railhead at Tikhvin falls into German hands
            <date>December 6 1941</date> A 200 mile –long roadway from Leningrad to Zaborie built in
        27 days at a cost of thousands of lives, begins operation. But as a lifeline it is almost
        useless, the greatest distance any lorry manages to cover in a single day is 20 miles.
            <date>December 9 1941</date> Soviet forces led by General Meretskov recapture Tikhvin.
        The railway resumes operation, bringing desperately needed supplies to Leningrad.
            <date>December 25 1941</date> Despite increased supplies from the outside some 3700
        Leningraders starve to death on Christmas Day, bringing the total for the month to 52,000.
        In Moscow the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet institutes a medal for the defence of
        Leningrad. The Attack on Moscow <date>September 26 1941</date> “Operation Typhoon” – the
        German offensive for the capture of Moscow is ordered. <date>October 2 1941</date>The
        offensive to capture Moscow begins in ideal weather conditions <date>October 7 1941 </date>
        Panzer spearheads seal off the Soviet forces in the Vyazma and Bryansk pockets.
            <date>October 8 1941</date> Heavy rains set in. The “mud season” begins to strangle the
        German mobile units, except for tanks. <date>October 14 1941</date> Resistance ends in the
        Vyazma pocket <date>October 19 1941</date> Stalin proclaims a state of siege in Moscow.
            <date>October 20 1941</date> Resistance ends in the Bryansk pocket, but many Soviet
        troops manage to escape the net. <date>October 20 – 25 1941</date> Stiffening Soviet
        resistance and struggling supply lines halt the original “Typhoon” offensive. New orders are
        issued for advances on more limited objectives to safeguard the German front line.
            <date>November 15 1941</date> After initial success, the second phase of the Moscow
        offensive is paralysed by 20 degree of frost and ever –strengthening Soviet forces.
            <date>November 27 1941</date> Panzer spearheads struggle to within 19 miles of the
        northern outskirts of Moscow, but are halted by fierce counter-attacks. South of Moscow, the
        advance German units reach Kashira, but are also halted. <date>December 5 1941</date> After
        obstinate argument, Hitler agrees to abandon the Moscow offensive for the winter. Army Group
        Centre begins to retreat to safer defensive positions. <date>December 5- 6 1941</date> The
        Soviet counter-offensive begins, at first the Kalinin / West Fronts to relieve the threat to
        Moscow. <date>December 13 1941</date> Moscow has been saved from the attack of Army Group
        Centre, but Stalin determines to extend the offensive to the entire Soviet / German front.
            <date>December 17 – 18 1941</date> Stalin orders Volkhov and North –Western Fronts to
        take the offensive against Army Group North. <date>December 26 – 30 1941</date> Red Army
        units land on the Kerch Peninsula to relieve Sebastopol 1942 <date>January 9 - 25
            1942</date> North – Western Volkhov, and Kalinin Fronts drive deep into the Whermacht’s
        rear but find their efforts too dissipated and their objectives too distant. German
        resistance stiffens. <date>January - February 1942</date> The Soviet offensive continues to
        win small victories in the Centre and North but fails in the South. By March 1942 all Soviet
        fronts have run out of resources – the offensive is over. <date>January 18 1942</date>
        Southern wing of the general Soviet winter offensive begins <date>January 24 1942</date>
        Barvenkovo captured <date>March 1942</date> Soviet winter offensive halts <date>May 8
            1942</date> German XI Army launches its attack against the Crimean Front <date>May 12
            1942</date> Russian South –West Front launches an offensive to break out of the
        Barvenkovo salient, thus forestalling a German offensive to liquidate it. <date>May 15
            1942</date> German forces break through on the Crimean Front and occupy the town of
        Kerch, forcing the Russians to evacuate the Kerch peninsula. The Crimean Front has
        collapsed. <date>May 17 1942</date> German counter-offensive against the Barvenkovo salient
        . Army Group Kleist attacks from the North and the VI Army from the South. <date>May 19
            1942</date> Soviet offensive is called off, but the German pincers cannot be halted.
            <date>May 23 1942</date> German forces link up, thus cutting off all Soviet troops in
        the salient. <date>June 2 1942</date> The Germans open up a five day barrage of Sevastopol
        with “super power” artillery, including 800-mm mortars. <date>June 7 1942</date> The German
        infantry assault on Sebastopol begins, supported by as many as 1,000 Luftwaffe sorties a
        day. But the Russians hold on. <date>June 10 – 26 1942</date> German offensives on the
        Volchansk and Kupyansk axes force the left wing of South –West Front back to the River
        Oskol. <date>June 30 1942</date> After 24 days of bitter fighting the Russians begin to
        evacuate Sebastopol. To commemorate the prolonged struggle the Presidium of the Supreme
        Soviet awards a special medal to the city’s defenders. Stalingrad <date>June 28 1942</date>
        The German summer offensive begins with a breakthrough at Kursk <date>July 5 1942</date>
        Army Group B reaches the Don River on either side of Voronezh <date>July 12 1942</date>
        STAVKA sets up a new “Stalingrad” Front <date>July 23 1942</date> Bock is dismissed. IV
        Panzer Army under Hoth is ordered to swing away from Stalingrad and assist I Panzer Army
        under Kleist to cross the Don. <date>July 25 1942</date> Kleist gets his light forces across
        the Don River. VI Army continues its advance toward Stalingrad, but fails to liquidate
        Russian bridgeheads on the West bank. <date>July 29 1942</date> Hoth’s Panzers cross the Don
        at Tsimlyanskaya. Kleist captures Proletarskaya. <date>August 10 1942</date> Von Paulus
        troops reach the outskirts of Stalingrad, while Hoth moves up to rejoin them. <date>August
            19 1942</date> First German attempts to storm Stalingrad <date>August 22 1942</date> XIV
        Panzer Corps force a narrow breach in the Russian perimeter at Vertyachi <date>August 23
            1942</date> Germans reach the bank of the Volga <date>August 23 -24</date> Luftwaffe
        makes a terror raid on Stalingrad <date>August 25</date> State of Emergency declared in
        Stalingrad. Heavy fighting halts the German advance. <date>September 13 1942</date> “Final”
        German attack on Stalingrad begins. A breakthrough in the Centre forces General Chuikov to
        commit his last reserves. But the German attack is halted. <date>September 24 1942</date>
        Franz Halder, Chief of the OKW is dismissed by Hitler. <date>October 4 1942</date> The
        fourth German attack at Stalingrad, directed at the Tractor Factory, the Barrikady and the
        Krasny Oktyabr, begins nearly three weeks of bitter fighting. <date>October 14 1942</date>
        Hitler orders all forces to take the defensive and stand fast except for those in the
        Stalingrad area and some small sectors in the Caucasus. <date>Early November 1942</date> The
        Red Army prepares a plan (Plan Uranus) for the relief of Stalingrad, a large scale operation
        to be carried out along a front of 250 miles. <date>November 19 1942</date> At exactly 07:30
        hours, some 3,500 Soviet guns and mortars open fire on the breakthrough sectors. The Soviet
        blow to free Stalingrad has begun. By the second day of the attack, mobile forces of
        South-West Front have advanced up to 25 miles. <date>November 20 1942</date> Stalingrad
        Front takes up the offensive. <date>November 21 1942</date> The onrush of Soviet armour
        forces General Paulus to move his headquarters from Golubinsky to Nizhne- Chirskaya. Hitler
        then orders Paulus to relocate his headquarters again near Gumrak. <date>November 23
            1942</date> On the fifth day of the counter-attack, South –West and Stalingrad Fronts
        link up, closing the ring around 22 German divisions, a total of about 330,000 men.
            <date>November 24 1942</date> The Red Army launches operations to annihilate the
        encircled German forces. But although the Red Army forces halve the territory held by
        Paulus, their numbers are insufficient to destroy his army. <date>December 12 1942</date>
        General Manstein launches Operation Winter Storm, a counter-strike with 13 divisions to
        relieve the trapped VI Army. Fighting rages for 11 days but the operation fails. Hoth’s
        “storm group” is halted 25 miles from the beleagured Germans at Stalingrad. Meanwhile,
        Soviet South –West Front handed the Germans a crushing blow, on the middle Don, North-West
        of Stalingrad. <date>December 24 1942</date> Soviet forces now attack Hoth’s relief group.
        The Germans withdraw, and by December 31 it is clear that the Red Army has fresh
        opportunities for a strategic offensive in the whole Southern sector. 1943 <date>January 4
            1943</date> STAVKA approves the plan for “Operation Ring” – the methodical dissection,
        of the trapped German forces and their destruction, unit by unit. <date>January 8
            1943</date> STAVKA proposes to Paulus that he capitulate, otherwise his forces will be
        annihilated. Paulus rejects the ultimatum. <date>January 10 1943</date> Operation Ring
        begins at 08:00 hours, the Red Army opens its final assault on von Paulus’ forces with a
        massive artillery bombardment. At 09:00 hours Don Front takes the offensive. <date>January
            31 1943</date> Field- Marshall Paulus trapped in Stalingrad, surrenders the Southern
        group of his army. Two days later General Schreck surrenders the Northern group. The VI Army
        is no more.</body>
</timeline>
