<?xml-model href="file:/E:/Chrome%20Downloads/sourceschema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <bibl>
        <author>Christopher Chant</author>
        <title level="a">Uman-Botosani Offensive Operation</title>
        <title>Codenames</title>
        <date when="2019-06-06">May 24 2018</date>
        <ref target="URL">https://codenames.info/operation/uman-botosani-offensive-operation/</ref>
    </bibl>
    <desc>
        <p>This was the Soviet part of the <operation name="Dniepr-Carpathian Offensive"
                >'Dniepr-Carpathian Offensive Operation'</operation> in the western part of Ukraine
            carried out by <leader name="Ivan S. Konev">Marshal Sovetskogo Soyuza Ivan S.
                Konev's</leader>
            <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front</army> against <leader
                name="Erich von Manstein">Generalfeldmarschall Erich von Manstein's</leader>
            <army group="Sud">Heeresgruppe 'Sud'</army> to split the German army group in two and
            open the way for a Soviet advance to the Dniestr and Prut rivers in eastern Romania
                (<date when="1944-03-05" to="1944-04-05">5 March/17 April 1944</date>).</p>
        <p>The operation's immediate purpose was to crush the <army group="Uman">German Gruppe
                'Uman'</army>, split <army group="Sud">Heeresgruppe 'Sud'</army> and retake the
            south-western part of Ukraine.</p>
    </desc>
    <body>
        <p>After the completion of the <operation name="Korsun-Shevchenkovsky Offensive"
                >'Korsun-Shevchenkovsky Offensive Operation'</operation>, the primary forces of the
            newly promoted <leader name="Ivan S. Konev">Konev's</leader>
            <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="681000">681,000-strong</manpower>
            <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front</army> were opposed by the
                <manpower who="Germany" n="400000">400,000 men</manpower> of <leader
                name="Otto Wohler">General Otto Wohler's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="8">8th Army</army> within <army group="Sud">Heeresgruppe
                'Sud'</army>. At the start of the operation, therefore, the Soviets had a 1.7/1
            superiority in manpower, almost 1.5/1 superiority in armour (<manpower
                who="Soviet Union" n="670">670</manpower> to <manpower who="Germany" n="450">450
                armoured fighting vehicles</manpower>), and just greater than 2.5/1 superiority in
            artillery (<manpower who="Soviet Union" n="8890">8,890</manpower> to <manpower
                who="Germany" n="3500">3,500 pieces</manpower>), and parity in aircraft.</p>
        <p>The Stavka's concept for the operation was the destruction of the <army group="infantry"
                n="8">8th Army</army>, the sundering of <army group="Sud">Heeresgruppe 'Sud'</army>,
            and the severing of the route by which <leader name="Hans-Valentin
            Hube"
                >Generaloberst Hans-Valentin Hube's</leader>
            <army group="Panzer" n="1">1st Panzerarmee</army> could pull back to the south. The main
            offensive was to be delivered from the staging areas at <city name="Vinograd"
                >Vinograd</city>, <city name="Zvenigorodok">Zvenigorodok</city>, and <city
                name="Shpola">Shpola</city> in the direction of <city name="Uman">Uman</city> 1.</p>
        <p>During their preparation for the operation, the <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd
                Ukrainian Front</army> and its subordinate army staffs paid great attention to the
            maximisation of their strength and the optimisation of their tactical and logistical
            organisation to ensure that the least possible effect would be made on the course of the
            operation by the rasputitsa, poor weather conditions, and need for many assault river
            crossings.</p>
        <p>The operation began on <date when="1944-03-05">5 March</date> on a 110-mile (175-km)
            sector of the front between <city name="Dnepropetrovsk">Dnepropetrovsk</city> and <city
                name="Belaya Tserkov">Belaya Tserkov</city>. A very substantial artillery
            bombardment opened the offensive, which then developed successfully. In order to
            increase the impact of the initial assault and develop the offensive along the primary
            axis, the <army group="Tank" n="2">2nd Tank Army</army> and <army group="Tank" n="5">5th
                Guards Tank Army</army> were introduced into the offensive on the first day. The
            offensive swept across the Gorny Tikach river on <date when="1944-03-08">8 March</date>,
            overran the Germans' last defensive line to the north-east of the Yuzhny Bug river, and
            continued its pursuit of the retreating German forces with the <army group="Tank" n="6"
                >6th Guards Tank Army</army> in the van ahead of the <army group="Tank" n="2">2nd
                Tank Army</army> and <army group="Tank" n="5">5th Guard Tank Army</army>. The Soviet
            forces took <city name="Uman">Uman</city> on <date when="1944-03-10">10 March</date>
            after scattering the five divisions of <leader name="Ernst-Eberhard Hell">General
                Ernst-Eberhard Hell's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="7">VII Corps</army>, and the advanced detachments of their
            armies then reached the Yuzhny Bug river, which they crossed on a 60-mile (100-km)
            front, again without any pause, by means of seized crossings, and also pontoon bridges,
            boats and other improvisations.</p>
        <p>So ensure that the pace of the advance was continued unabated, the <army group="Tank"
                n="6">6th Guards Tank Army</army> took over the lead after the crossing of the
            Yuzhny Bug river. The tank armies thus continued their progress toward the Dniestr
            river, and on <date when="1944-03-17">17 March</date> advance units of the front's right
            wing established bridgeheads on the Dniestr's right bank to the south of the <city
                name="Mogilev-Podolsky">Mogilev-Podolsky</city> area.</p>
        <p>By this time, therefore, Soviet units had entered Moldova, and the <army
                group="Ukrainian Front" n="1">1st</army> and <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd
                Ukrainian Front</army> had succeeded in their object of splitting <army group="Sud"
                >Heeresgruppe 'Sud'</army> in two. Now divided from the <army group="Panzer" n="1"
                >1st Panzerarmee</army>, the <army group="infantry" n="8">8th Army</army> was
            reassigned to <leader name="Ewald von Kleist">Generalfeldmarschall Ewald von
                Kleist's</leader> (from <date when="1944-03-25">25 March</date>
            <leader name="Ferdinand Schorner">Generalfeldmarschall Ferdinand Schorner's</leader>)
                <army group="A">Heeresgruppe 'A'</army>.</p>
        <p>Konev now switched his <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front's</army>
            focus to this army group, which <leader name="Nikolai F. Vatutin">General Nikolai F.
                Vatutin's</leader>
            <army group="Ukrainian Front">1st Ukrainian Front</army> was already enveloping from the
            north. An opportunity arose for the <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian
                Front's</army> to attack to the south-west and thus cut the lines of retreat
            available to <army group="A">Heeresgruppe 'A'</army> to the west of the Dniestr river
            and destroy it in co-operation with <leader name="Rodion Ya. Malinovsky">General Rodion
                Ya. Malinovsky's</leader>
            <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="3">3rd Ukrainian Front</army>. The <army
                group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front's</army> 40th Army, under <leader
                name="Filipp F. Zhmachenko">General Leytenant Filipp F. Zhmachenko</leader>, was
            advancing along the Dniestr river's eastern bank and was now given the task of cutting
            the <army group="Panzer" n="1">1st Panzerarmee's</army> lines of retreat to the
            south-west, in the process collaborating with troops of the <army
                group="Ukrainian Front" n="1">1st Ukrainian Front</army> in the destruction of the
            German forces encircled by the <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="1">1st Ukrainian
                Front</army> at <city name="Kamenets-Podolsky">Kamenets-Podolsky</city> in the
                <operation name="Proskurov-Chernovtsy Offensive">'Proskurov-Chernovtsy Offensive
                Operation'</operation>. Brushing aside a German counterattack effort at <city
                name="Khotyn">Khotyn</city>, they pressed home the attack from the bridgehead to the
            Dniestr river.</p>
        <p>The <army group="infantry" n="27">27th Army</army> and <army group="infantry" n="52">52nd
                Army</army>, together with detachments of the <army group="Tank" n="2">2nd Tank
                Army</army> and <army group="Tank" n="6">6th Guards Tank Army</army>, advanced to
            the Prut river, and on <date when="1944-03-26">26 March</date> reached the
            Soviet/Romanian border on an 55-mile (85-km) front to the north of <city name="Ungheni"
                >Ungheni</city>. On the night of <date when="1944-03-28" to="1944-03-29">28/29
                March</date> the <army group="Ukrainian Front" n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front's</army>
            forces completed an assault crossing of the Prut river from the march, thereby taking
            the war onto Romanian territory.</p>
        <p>Towards the <date when="1944-04-15">middle of April</date> the front's right wing reached
            the Carpathian mountains, after taking <city name="Botosani">Botosani</city>, and
            approached <city name="Iasi">Iasi (Jassy)</city> and <city name="Chisinau">Chisinau
                (Kishinev)</city> from the north. In the hope of saving the southern wing of their
            front from complete disintegration, the Germans moved 18 divisions and three brigades,
            their last strategic reserve in the southern sector, to this part of the front. In the
            face of increasing resistance and its own increasing exhaustion of men and supplies, in
            the <date when="1944-04-15">middle of April</date> the <army group="Ukrainian Front"
                n="2">2nd Ukrainian Front</army> was forced to go on the defensive at <city
                name="Dubasari">Dubasari</city> to the north of <city name="Iasi">Iasi</city> and
            some 37 miles (60 km) to the south of <city name="Botosani">Botosani</city>.</p>
        <p>As a result the <operation name="Uman-Botosani Offensive">'Uman-Botosani Offensive
                Operation'</operation>, the <army group="infantry" n="8">8th Army</army> was
            destroyed and the <army group="Panzer" n="1">1st Panzerarmee</army> partially destroyed,
            while <army group="Sud">Heeresgruppe 'Sud'</army> was split into <army
                group="Sudukraine">Heeresgruppe 'Sudukraine'</army> under <leader
                name="Ferdinand Schorner">Schorner</leader>, and <army group="Nordukraine"
                >Heeresgruppe 'Nordukraine'</army> under <leader name="Walter Model"
                >Generalfeldmarschall Walter Model</leader>. The offensive had <casualties n="10"
                unit="divisions">cost 10 Axis divisions</casualties> some <casualties n="50" unit="percent">50% to
                75% of their troops</casualties> and almost all of their heavy weapons and equipment
            as the Soviets advanced some 125 to 155 miles (200 to 250 km), in the process taking
            significant parts of western Ukraine and Moldova before entering the north-eastern
            regions of Romania.</p>
        <p>The Soviet advance then became the <operation name="1st Iasi-Chisinau Offensive">'1st
                Iasi-Chisinau Offensive Operation'</operation> of <date when="1944-04-08"
                to="1944-06-06">8 April/6 June</date>. This ended with the Battle of <city
                name="Targu Frumos">Targu Frumos</city>, which stabilised the front until <date
                when="1944-08-01">August 1944</date>, when the <operation
                name="2nd Iasi-Chisinau Strategic Offensive">'2nd Iasi-Chisinau Strategic Offensive
                Operation'</operation> destroyed <army group="Sudukraine">Heeresgruppe
                'Sudukraine'</army> and restarted the Soviet drive to the west. It is worth noting
            that the <operation name="Uman-Botosani Offensive">'Uman-Botosani Offensive
                Operation'</operation> was the first in which three tank armies were used
            simultaneously as the main breakthrough force on a narrow sector of the front. The
            offensive was also undertaken under the conditions of spring floods and rasputitsa. The
            Soviet armies made six assault crossings straight from the march, the rivers in question
            being the Gorniy Tikach, Yuzhny Bug, Dniestr, Reut, Prut and Siret.</p>
        <p>So far as casualties were concerned, the Soviets admitted the loss of <casualties
                n="70000">70,000 men killed</casualties> and <casualties n="200000">200,000
                wounded</casualties>, and the Axis losses, excluding the Romanians, were in the
            order of <casualties n="45000">45,000 men killed</casualties> and <casualties n="25000"
                >25,000 taken prisoner</casualties>, though the Soviets claimed the figures were
                <casualties n="118400">118,400 killed</casualties> and <casualties n="27393">27,393
                taken prisoner</casualties>.</p>
        <p>The forces involved were <leader name="Sergei G. Trofimenko">General Leytenant Sergei G.
                Trofimenko's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="27">27th Army</army>, <leader name="Konstantin A. Koroteyev"
                >General Leytenant Konstantin A. Koroteyev's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="2">52nd Army</army>, <leader name="Ilya K. Smirnov">General
                Leytenant Ilya K. Smirnov's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="4">4th Guards Army</army>, <leader name="Semyon I. Bogdanov's"
                >General Leytenant Semyon I. Bogdanov's</leader>
            <army group="Tank" n="2">2nd Tank Army</army>, <leader name="Pavel A. Rotmistrov"
                >General Leytenant Pavel A. Rotmistrov's</leader>
            <army group="Tank" n="5">5th Guards Tank Army</army> and <leader
                name="Andrei G.
            Kravchenko">General Leytenant Andrei G.
                Kravchenko's</leader>
            <army group="Tank" n="6">6th Guards Tank Army</army> (<manpower who="Soviet Union"
                n="415">415 tanks</manpower> and <manpower who="Soviet Union" n="147">147
                self-propelled guns</manpower>), supported by <leader name="Sergei K. Goryunov"
                >General Leytenant Sergei K. Goryunov's</leader>
            <army group="Air" n="5">5th Air Army</army>. <leader name="Nikolai I. Krylov">General
                Leytenant Nikolai I. Krylov's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="7">7th Army</army> and <leader name="Mikhail S. Shumilov"
                >General Leytenant Mikhail S. Shumilov's</leader>
            <army group="infantry" n="5">5th Guards Army</army> delivered supporting attacks from
            the region of <city name="Kirovograd">Kirovograd</city> in the direction of <city
                name="Novoukrainka">Novoukrainka</city>.</p>
    </body>
</xml>
